... look closer
American Beauty is a drama film directed by Sam Mendes.
Lester Burnham, a depressed suburban father in a mid-life crisis, decides to turn his hectic
life around after developing an infatuation with his daughter's attractive friend.
Lester Burnham, played by Kevin Spacey.
Carolyn Burnham, played by Annette Bening.
Jane Burnham, played by Thora Birch.
Ricky Fitts, played by Wes Bentley.
Angela Hayes, played by Mena Suvari.
Buddy Kane, played by Peter Gallagher.
American Beauty is a 1999 American black comedy and psychological drama film written by
Alan Ball and directed by Sam Mendes in his feature directorial debut.
Kevin Spacey stars as Lester Burnham, an advertising executive who has a midlife crisis when he
becomes infatuated with his teenage daughter's best friend, played by Mena Suvari.
Annette Bening stars as Lester's materialistic wife, Carolyn, and
Thora Birch plays their insecure daughter, Jane.
Wes Bentley, Chris Cooper, Peter Gallagher, and Allison Janney co-star.
Academics have described the film as satirizing how beauty and personal satisfaction are perceived by the American middle class; further
analysis has focused on the film's explorations of romantic and paternal love, sexuality, materialism and self-liberation.
After being filmed in California from December 1998 to February 1999, American Beauty was released by DreamWorks
Pictures in North America on September 17, 1999, receiving widespread critical and popular acclaim.
It was the second-best-reviewed American film of the year behind Being John Malkovich and grossed over $350
million worldwide against its $15-million budget, becoming the ninth highest-grossing film of 1999.
DreamWorks launched a major campaign to increase American Beauty's chances of Oscar success following
its controversial Best Picture snub for Saving Private Ryan (1998) the previous year.
At the 72nd Academy Awards, the film won five Oscars, including Best Picture, along with Best Director for Mendes,
Best Actor for Spacey, Best Original Screenplay for Ball, and Best Cinematography for Conrad L.
The film was nominated for and won many other awards and
honors, mainly for directing, writing, and acting.
The film explores themes of estate agent,
adultery, coming out, first time, virgin.
The tone is lighthearted and dark and thought_provoking.